The Leonard Woolsey Bacon Papers
Yale University Music Library
The Leonard Woolsey Bacon Papers
1887-1926
Misc. Ms. 54
Yale University Music Library
1
2 boxes
Music and correspondence by the American composer and physician Leonard Woolsey Bacon, Jr. (1865-1939)
Bacon, Leonard Woolsey, 1865-1939
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Related Materials
Researchers may also wish to consult the Bacon-Schneeloch Family Papers, MS 707, in Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University.
Arrangement
In 3 series as follows: I. Music by Bacon. II. Music by Others. III. Correspondence.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of holograph sketches, scores, and parts for 27 musical compositions by Leonard Woolsey Bacon, Jr., including songs, piano pieces, and chamber music. The Papers also hold a number of works by other composers in copyists' manuscripts. Two letters are also included.
Biographical / Historical
Leonard Woolsey Bacon, Jr. was born in Stamford, Connecticut on February 24, 1865. He should not be confused with his father, Leonard Woolsey Bacon (1830-1907), a clergyman, writer, and doctor. Like many members of his family, Leonard, Jr. attended Yale College (Class of 1888), where he helped found the orchestra. He earned the M.D. from the Yale School of Medicine in 1892, and also studied at numerous other American and European universities. Bacon had a long and distinguished career as a physician in New Haven, but he was also a composer and church organist, and it is his musical activities that are represented in this collection. In 1892 Bacon married Emma Waleska Schneeloch, a prominent singer who usually performed with her sister Emilie. (For more on the Schneeloch Sisters, see MSS 6, the Schneeloch Family Papers.) Emma died in 1925, and two years later Bacon married Esther Louise Oleson. He died in Hamden, Connecticut on January 8, 1939.
Piano music; Sonatas (Violin and piano) -- Scores and parts; Songs; Bacon, Emma Waleska Schneeloch, 1862-1925; Bacon, Leonard Woolsey, 1865-1939
- Music by Bacon, Series I
  - Chamber Music, I.A
    - Larghetto (String Quartet), 1887
      - Score (Box 1, Folder 1)
        General
        (Holograph)
      - Score and Piano Reduction (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Piano Reductions (2) (Box 1, Folder 1)
        (Holographs)
      - Parts (2 sets) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Song of Shilric, 1926
      (Words from Ossian)
      String Quartet with Vocal Obligato (Baritone)
      - Score (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Score (Box 1, Folder 3)
        (Photographic reproduction)
      - Score (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Score (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Arrangement for Voice and Piano (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Vocal part alone, vocal part with piano reduction, sketches (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Parts (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Sketches (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Organ Music, I.B
    - Hymn Book - Sentences to Follow the Lord's Prayer in the Morning Service at the Woodland Church, Philadelphia (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (Most hymns composed and/or arranged by Z.W. Bacon, Jr.)
    - Hymn Book (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (Most hymns composed and/or arranged by L.W. Bacon, Jr.)
  - Piano Music, I.C
    - Air varié dédié à sa nièce, 1925
      - Photographic reproductions (3) (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Sketches (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Includes an obligato part [violin?]
    - Barcarolle, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Dirge, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Holographs (2)
      (2nd holograph incomplete)
    - Revery of Long Ago, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      (2nd holograph includes an obligato part [violin?]
  - Violin Music, I.D
    - "Long, Long Ago", n.d.
      - Score (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Holograph
      - Scores (4) (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Each includes a separate violin part
        (Photographic reproductions)
      - Score (Box 1, Folder 12)
        (Incomplete)
      - Violin part only (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Sonata For The Violin, 1926
      - Score with separate violin part (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Score (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Scores (2) (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Violin part only (2) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Vocal Music, I.E
    - [Balow My Babe], n.d.
      - Scores (2) (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Sketches (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Beim Schneida, beim Binda" (A Suabian Song)
      - Scores (2) (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Score, incomplete, in the inside of [Balow My Babe] (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - [La Belle Dame sans Merci]
      - Scores (2) (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Vocal part incomplete (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Set of Words (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Christians Awake! Salute the Happy Morn (Chorale hymn) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Dû bist mîn (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Scores (2)
    - When We Parted (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - The Grief of Those Who Cannot Mourn (Song for Baritone Voice), 1887
      - Scores (3) (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Scores (3) (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Sketches (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Sets of Words (3) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Hear, My Beloved (Box 2, Folder 6)
      (Holographs) (2)
    - Hymns (Box 2, Folder 6)
      See: Hymn Books under Organ Music
    - [It Is Not Mine to Sing], 1924 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - [Kunde jeg Roser male]
      - Score (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Vocal part only (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - The Lamp of Love, 1926
      - Scores (2) (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Set of Words (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - The Song of Shilric (Box 2, Folder 7)
      See: The Song of Shilric under Chamber Music
    - There Was a Little Girl, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - They that Sow in Tears Shall Reap in Joy (3-part chorus [SAA?]), 1887
      - Scores (2) (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Score (Box 2, Folder 10)
        (Photographia reproduction)
    - [Thy Ways Are Ways of Pleasantness and Peace] (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - When We Parted (Box 2, Folder 11)
      See: Dû Bist Mîn under Vocal Music
    - [With Thee to Wander]
      - Score (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Set of Words (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Music by Others, Series II
  - Unidentified Sketches (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Amami (Love Me) Song with piano, Rizzo, G. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    (Manuscript)
    Signed by Millie Schneeloch
  - Ave Maria Of Wagner Voice and Piano, Wagner, Richard, 1813-1883 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    (Manuscript copy)
  - Der Schönste Bub War Henny Quartet for piano, violin, cello, and voice, Unknown (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Score and Parts
  - Trub, Trub Ist Mein Auge Quartet for piano, violin, cello, and voice, Unknown (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Gloria Dei Voices in Unison, Pehner, Clara Bell (Box 2, Folder 13)
    (Inscribed to Mrs. Bacon, 1903)
    (signed holograph)
  - Herr Der Welt Four-part chorus with solo quartet, Unknown (Box 2, Folder 13)
    SATB
  - [I Saw A Little Kiss] Song with piano, Unknown (Box 2, Folder 13)
    [Signed?] by Mrs. E. Harry Raymond
  - A Life Lesson Tenor in B-flat, Nevin, Ethelbert, 1862-1901 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Signed by Ralph Hugo Schneeloch
  - Rondo Hongroise Trio for violin, cello, piano, Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Trio For Pianoforte, Violin & Violoncello, Unknown (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Trio For Violin, Violincello, And Klavier, 1898; Unknown (Box 2, Folder 16)
    (Name undecipherable)
  - Trio For Violin, Violincello, And Klavier, 1900; Unknown (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Unidentified - Cello Part (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, Series III
  - Autograph letter to Emma Schneeloch from L.W. Bacon, [1891?] (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Autograph letter signed to - (name undecipherable) from "Ben" - [brother of L.W. Bacon?], 1888 (Box 2, Folder 19)